Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 8 -- Letters to Franklin 1783 December-1786 Mss.B.F85inventory08
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 November 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Sent the books to Messrs, de la Rochefoucauld, de Malesherbes and de Barbançon; returns their acknowledgments to Franklin. Passy at Present a desert; no one left but M. [Le Ray] de Chaumont and himself. Affectionate messages and pleadings for news.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 November 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Morgan, John Jr. Prospect
    Begging Franklin's acceptance on his father's part, of a small box of honey in the comb.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 November 24; A.L.S. 4p.; Barbançon, comte de
    Thanking him for the catalogue. M. le Due d'Orléans desires to have two boxes of seeds sent him from America, to be planted in April, 1787; wishes a box on his account; begs Franklin to recommend a botanist who will carry out this commission in the most careful manner possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 November 24; A.L.S. 5p.; Nixon, William. Savannah
    Franklin's letter on his behalf to General [Anthony] Wayne has been extremely successful; has a school which brings him in near three hundred pounds sterling a year; informed of a report circulated in Charleston accusing him of forging the letter of recommendation to Gen. Wayne; begs Franklin to write a line to Judge Burke, of Charleston refuting this accusation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 November 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Chaumont, Le Ray de, fils
    Will call on Franklin that day, in order to examine and correct the error mentioned.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 December 1; A.L.S. 3p.; Chastellux, marquis de
    Recommending Major Lattier, an Irishman in the service of France. Five months before, forwarded the two volumes of his travels of America; if Franklin has troubled himself to read them, desires his opinion thereon. Received two months before a diploma [of Doctor of Laws (conferred in 1782)] from the Academy of Philadelphia addressed to him by Franklin, which he desires to acknowledge.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 December 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Stiles, Ezra. Yale College
    Fear of trespassing on Franklin's time the reason of these late congratulations on his return to America; wrote a number of letters to him during his Embassy in Paris but never received any answers. His great respect and esteem for Franklin. The hearer of this, Mr. [Noah] Webster [Jr.], has had great success in New Haven with his lectures. Many subjects on which he would be glad of Franklin's opinion.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 December 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Banks, Sir Joseph. London
    Acknowledging the Transactions of the [American] Philosophical Society, which were duly presented to the Royal Society. Perfect harmony reigning at present in the Royal Society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 December 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Randolph, Gov. Edmund. Richmond
    His anxiety for the well-being of the Federal Government must be his excuse for sending the enclosed Act of their Legislature and for repeating his request that Franklin would give his serious attention to the present American crisis. Enumerates the gentlemen appointed by Virginia for the Convention at Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 December 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Mckean, Thomas. Philadelphia
    Announcing that five gentlemen have been appointed to wait upon Franklin and request his name and patronage for a German College proposed to be erected in the Borough of Lancaster.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 December 9; A.L.S. 4p.; Chalut and Arnous, Abbés
    Acknowledging the three cakes of vegetable soap. The consolation they derive from contemplating the joys of a free country like America. Wide-spread regret at Franklin's departure from France. Reflections on the state of affairs in Holland. Reminding him of the desire of their friend M. Humbert Gerbier to be elected a member of the [American] Philosophical Society. Sent the portrait of the late Abbé de Mably to Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson, who promised to deliver it to Franklin. Message to Franklin's grandson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 December 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Brillon, Mme
    Her unalterable affection and friendship. Illness of her husband and children; misses his wise and helpful philosophy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 December 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Rhoads, Ann. Philadelphia
    Concerning an account due her late husband by Mr. Robert Smith; refusal of his son and administrator, Mr. John Smith, to pay her one cent; unless she can obtain payment, will be turned out of doors; applies to Franklin for assistance; sends him a certified copy of the award in her husband's favor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 December 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Sr
    Recommending his son-in-law, Mr. Samuel Bradford, to Franklin's civilities.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 December 17; A.L.S. 3p.; Saussure, Horace Bénédict de
    Sending Franklin the second volume of his Voyages dans les Alpes. Account of the first ascent to the top of Mont Blanc, made by M. Paccard; his own first attempt unsuccessful; expects to accomplish it the following summer.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 275; Bigelow, IX, 352).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 December 23; A.L.S. 1p.; The State of Pennsylvania's Invalid Guards
    Requests Dr. Franklin to bestow a Christmas gift on the poor unfortunate fellows who fell in the glorious cause of America; the request is made to drink to the health of the glorious Washington under whom they fought so nobly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 December 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Bourne, Dominique. New York
    Explaining how he came to open the enclosed letter addressed to Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 December 29; A.L.S. 3p.; Birckenstock, J.M. Vienna
    Presenting him with several copies of his Latin work on the Life and character of Frederick the Great.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 December 30; L.S. 1p.; Jay, John
    Acknowledging his favor of the 21st ult., with the enclosed papers; letters from Sir Edward Newenham on the same subject previously received; all the papers shall be laid before Congress as soon as they make a House.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 December 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Childs, Francis
    Recommending to his good offices a gentleman of great literary accomplishments, John O'Connor, Esq.; his object in visiting Philadelphia is to solicit subscriptions for his book, Anecdotes of Louis XVI of France, which he (Childs) is printing.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786; A.L.S. 1p.; Biddle, Charles
    Announcing that the election for an officer of excise, for the Country of Bucks will take place that day.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786.]; A.L.S.1p.; Biddle, Charles
    Desires a few lines which may effectually contradict the report that Franklin has complained and disapproved of his conduct.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786?]; A.L.S. 1p.; Biddle, Charles
    Information from Mr. [Col. John] Bull of some disturbances at Wyoming; suggests a meeting of the Council at Franklin's house or the State House.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786?]; A.L.S. 2p.; Bridgen, Edward
    His ambition to present the States with the handsomest and best copper coin in the world. Acknowledging Franklin's singular service in obtaining the restoration of his estate in North Carolina.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786]; A.L.S. 1p.; Duffield, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Sends a description of the White Walnut.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786.]; L. in 3d L. in 3d P. 1p.; Ellinkhuysen, Major
    Begging Franklin to Write a few lines to his father in Rotterdam, stating that the lands lately purchased by the Major on the West Branch of the Susquehannah, are in an improved and valuable part of the State.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786]; A.L.S. 1p.; Farrel, Margaret
    Begging for a loan.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [before Aug.]; Poem, 2p.; Feutry, Aimé Ambroise Joseph
    Fable, in imitation of the English of Dr. Percival, on the experiment of pouring oil to calm the waters during a storm. "Envoi'' to Franklin as a tribute of gratitude for his election to membership in the [American] Philosophical Society at Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786.] Saturday; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Hamilton, Mr
    Will wait on the President next Monday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786?]; A.L.S. 3p.; Helvétius, Madame Ligniville
    Speaks with delight of past days spent with Franklin; pleasure his letters give her. Her true friends always with her; absolutely necessary one to the other. Sends a redingote for Mrs. [Richard] Bache, which may serve as a model; messages to Benjamin [Franklin Bache]. Afraid he will be unable to decipher her scrawl.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786?]; A.L.S. 3p.; Hill, James. London
    Sending him the locket about which he wrote before; explains its construction and allegorical meaning.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786.]; A.L.S. 1p.; Hopkinson, Francis
    Begs for the return of his "Law-Suit" which Franklin must have perused by this time; inclined to publish it; desires Franklin's advice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Circa 1786]; A.L.S. 1p.; Huck, Cille
    Begging a loan of ten pounds; promises to repay it in a year.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786]; A.L.S. 1p.; Huck, Cille
    Asks for help in her financial affairs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786.]; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Desiring Franklin to send him, by the first opportunity, a small supply of holly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786?]; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Greatly pleased with Franklin's observations on the lightning-rod; their number increasing steadily. M. [Thomas] Paine's model of a bridge not yet arrived. Introductions for M. Manasseh Cutler. His brother [Julien David Le Roy] delighted with his election to Franklin's illustrious [American Philosophical] Society. Books he promises to send him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786?]; A.L.S. 8p.; Limozin, Andrew
    Forwarding to Congress an Act passed in the King's Council for sundry favors granted the American trade. Desires to be legally appointed Agent for America with powers on behalf of his son Edward; his past services as Agent; assistance given by him to destitute Americans who escaped to France from English prisons.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786.] Second day; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Mifflin, John Sr
    Requesting Dr. Franklin's acceptance of a few peaches.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786.] Wednesday; L. in 3d P. 1p.; North, Major William
    Will attend on the President Friday next.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786.]; A.L.S. 1p.; Parker, Sally
    Request for money.
    A.E. by Dr. Franklin. An impudent beggar who has heretofore imposed on me and my son to the amount of about £25.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786.]; A.L.S. 2p.; Pollard, William
    Increasing number of robberies in Philadelphia; suggests the expediency of opening all letters to persons of evil fame; encloses a list of their names.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786.]; A.L.S. 1p.; Swanwick, John
    Sending the pamplet which he desires to dedicate to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786.]; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Swanwick, John. Philadelphia
    Asks for the letter for Mr. [John] Adams which he promised.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786 ?]; A.L.S. 1p.; Vaughan, Samuel. Jr
    Account of his failure to see the elder or younger Wharton; has written them to request copies of the letters accompanying the remittances made to Mr. [Francis] Coffyn.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786.] Monday morning; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Vaughan, John
    Is prevented by an indispensable engagement from waiting on the President.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Webster, Noah Jr. Philadelphia
    Begging Franklin's perusal of the enclosed papers relative to a proposed selection of essays on America, to be used in the ["Grammatical] Institute [of the English Language"]. Returning the first volume of Elphinstone's "Principles."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786.]; L. 1p.; -----, -----. Postmarked Carnarvon
    Requests him to locate, if possible, a young man named Price Hughes, who went to Philadelphia in 1768, and who is now heir to an estate of about £150 a year.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. 2p.; -----, -----
    Proposal to erect a provincial Bank by Act of Assembly. The management to be in the hands of the gentlemen now Trustees of the Loan Office.
    (Fragment.)